Now, without a doubt, Spain was the
grand pooha of imperial powers in the
Americas from 1491 to6007. So, let's
visit with these rascally colonizers for
a spell and see how they became the
great lidless colonial eye of Sauron.
Should be fun. So, if you're ready to
get them brain cows milked, let's get to
it. Now, hopefully you recall from the
last couple of videos that the first
European state to roll the dice and try
to access Asian markets by sailing west
across the Atlantic was Spain. And
here's a fun little rhyme about that. In
1492, Columbus sailed the ocean blue and
established Spain's claim to conquer
everybody's crap, too. Anyway, Columbus
ended up making no less than four trips
to the Caribbean over the course of
about a decade. And he tried to get the
Spaniards who were with him to build
houses and towns, over which Columbus
aimed to rule as governor. But, as it
turned out, those Spaniards just wanted
gold. And when the indigenous groups cut
off trade with them, the colonizers
began taking it by force. Oh, by the
way, if you want note guys to follow
along with this video and all my videos,
you can check that link in the
description. Anyway, not long after
that, the Spanish went ahead and
conquered and subjugated various islands
in the Caribbean. But wouldn't you know
it, they got lusty for even more wealth.
So, Spain sent more concistadors to the
mainland to see if anything needed
conquering over there. And they sure
found some eligible societies. And
apparently, someone in the Spanish court
decided that it was just rude to
brutally subjugate a people without a
proper explanation. So, King Ferdinand
and Queen Isabella issued a legal
document known as the Roqua Meento,
which claimed that the Pope had given
Spain biblical authority to rule in the
Americas and threatened violence to any
indigenous group that defied that order.
And I'm sure when the indigenous people
heard this read in their towns, they
were like, "Oh, the Pope said so. That
makes so much more sense to me now.
Thank you for explaining it. It would
help you conquer if we just like laid
down or no." The indigenous people
emphatically did not respond like that.
First of all, because you know that's
stupid. But second, and more
importantly, the document was read out
loud in Spanish. And as it turns out,
they did not know Spanish. So this
document was more of an example of the
Spanish trying to justify to themselves
that they had rights to conquer and
pillage in the Americas. Anyway, by
1521, the concistador Hernand Cortez had
toppled the mighty Aztec Empire and
claimed it for Spain. And even though he
had relatively few Spaniards with him,
and the Aztecs eventually resisted the
attack, Cortez had two advantages.
First, Spanish diseases like smallpox
weakened the Aztecs, including some of
their vital leadership, and that made
them vulnerable to attack. Second,
Cortez allied with several indigenous
groups who had been under the authority
of the Aztecs and fought with the
Spanish to secure their own liberation.
Anyway, a few years later, another
concisador by the name of Francisco
Pizarro used similar tactics to defeat
and conquer the Inca Empire in South
America. And because of the metric
buttloads of gold and silver Spain was
gaining from these two empires, they
went ahead and cranked their
colonization efforts up to 11. Okay, so
now that the Spanish got their initial
windfall of wealth from their American
colonies, they needed to figure out how
to keep that boom boom flowing reliably.
And so they introduced the incomienda
system which by definition was a system
of coerced labor in which the Spanish
crown granted tracks of land to Spanish
incomanderos who forced the indigenous
people within its borders into mining
and plantation-based agriculture. And to
be fair, the Spanish themselves wouldn't
say they forced anyone into labor. Now
by their reckoning, there was a mutual
benefit to encomando. Yes, the
encomandos required indigenous people to
work for them, but in return the
encouanderos had to provide protection
and Christianization. And to the
Spanish, that was a great deal for those
primitive indigenous folks. But to be
absolutely clear, and comedend is just a
fancy word for the Spanish flavor of
slavery. It's easy to get lost in all
the jargon like coerced labor, but as my
grandpappy used to say, if it looks like
a duck and quacks like a duck, it's
probably slavery. Anyway, the Spanish
used the encoma system as their main way
to extract wealth from their colonies.
And there were two sources of that
wealth. First was mining for gold and
silver, and the second was the export of
cash crops like sugarcane and tobacco
and cotton. Now, we'll talk more in unit
2 about the brutality of Spanish and
comeenda and some reforms that were
made. But for now, you just need to
remember that in order to extract wealth
from their colonies, the Spanish
enslaved Native Americans to mine and
farm within the bounds of Spanish
territory. And then here's where I tell
you that Spanish reliance on indigenous
labor began to break down for two
reasons. First, enslaved indigenous
workers knew the land much better than
the Spanish on account of, you know,
like their ancestral home and all, and
that made escape an increasingly
frequent phenomenon. Second, indigenous
slaves kept dying from Spanish diseases.
So, as the Spanish considered that
development, it was a real moment of
contemplation and introspection. You
know, our workers are dying and running
away, and we've destroyed the very
fabric of their ancient societies.
>> And it really makes you think about
whether we're doing the right thing or
not.
>> See?
>> Hey, are you guys thinking what I'm
thinking?
>> See?
>> Okay, let's say it together on three. 1
2 3. Leave the Americas for Africans to
do the work.
>> Oh, see. And that's how the Spanish
solved their indigenous labor problem.
Namely, by increasingly relying on the
importation of enslaved Africans to work
the mines and the plantations. So,
Spanish merchants and other colonial
powers as well partnered with West
African groups in order to trade goods.
Guns being the most desirable good for
enslaved laborers from the African
interior. And many of those African
groups involved in the trade became
wealthy and powerful owing to the
superior weaponry they gained in trading
with the Europeans. However, I should
mention that the African slave trade had
existed for centuries before this
period. The slaves usually being
prisoners of war and local conflict.
Europeans simply tapped into this system
and in doing so drove the demand for
African slaves way up and thus increased
the necessity for African warfare and
the capture of slaves. Anyway, once
purchased, Africans were shipped across
the Atlantic via the notorious middle
passage. The people were crammed onto
these ships like cargo and the death
rate was somewhere around 20% on these
ships owing to the rapid spread of
disease and malnutrition. And once they
arrived on the American shores, they
were sold to the Spanish. And this
arrangement solved both of their labor
problems. First of all, Africans were
from, you know, like Africa and so they
didn't know the land in the Americas and
thus were less likely to escape. And
second, Africans had been in contact
with smallox and measles and other
diseases for centuries and had better
immunity and thus were more reliable
for, you know, like not dying. And so
for those reasons, African slavery
gradually became the dominant coerced
labor system in the Americas. Okay. Now,
the final feature of Spanish America
that you need to know is how the Spanish
imposed a completely new and foreign
social structure in the Americas. is
known as the Spanish cast system, but in
other classes you may have heard it
called the casta system, but you know,
it's the same thing. Don't get confused.
Now, if I had to guess, when you hear
cast system, you most likely think of
India, and you'd be right to do so. In
South Asian history, the cast system has
divided their society into rigid layers
at birth. The people at the top were
generally wealthy and powerful, while
the people at the bottom were treated as
disposable and held no social power in
the system. And until recently, there
wasn't really any way a person can move
from one level to the other without, you
know, like dying and being reborn.
Anyway, the Spanish cast system in the
Americas resembled this scenario in a
lot of important ways. You see, almost
none of the traditional Spanish nobility
who held wealth and power in Spain
migrated to the new world. Therefore,
the most powerful concisadors who
established Spain's empire in the new
world worked to impose a new social
hierarchy on the peoples there so that
they might drink liberally from the cup
of wealth and power that they were
denied in the homeland. The result was
the casta system which organized
colonial society into a ranked social
hierarchy that was based on race and
heredity. Basically, the more white
blood a person had, the more social
power they had, and the less white
blood, the less social power. So, not
surprisingly, the pure Spanish
themselves were at the top. And then the
indigenous Americans, and the Africans
were at the bottom. And then contact
between these groups resulted in
something like 40 separate divisions on
the hierarchy that the Spanish used to
organize and define the social
categories of their colonial
possessions. You see, prior to the
imposing of the cast system, native
peoples were part of a wide variety of
linguistic and cultural groups. But the
cast system erased much of that cultural
complexity and ordered their society by
the standards of a small minority of
Spanish elite. And then whatever
category a person found themselves in
dictated the kind of education they
could receive or the kinds of
occupations or even the amount of
tribute or tax payments they were
responsible for. And then this system
also altered the spatial makeup of towns
and villages. For example, Spanish
settlements had a church and a town hall
in the center which was home to those in
the upper levels of the social hierarchy
and then those who were on the lower
levels were forced to live on the
outskirts of the settlement. And by
these means the Spanish consolidated
control over all their American
possessions. Well, okay. You can click
here to watch my other topic videos for
unit one, or you can click here to grab
my video note guides, which is going to
help you get all the contents of this
course firmly crammed into your brain
folds. I'm glad you came around and I'll
catch you on the flip-flop.